Pamela Moore papers 13202800
Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Series I: Manuscripts and Related Materials, 1942-2013 [Bulk Dates: 1950-1964]
  - Subseries I.7: Drafts and Fragments, 1942-1978, undated
    Some items are clearly related to works elsewhere in Series I, but many are unidentified.
    - Ideas, undated (Box 12, Folder 8)
      This includes various notes. It also includes additional Treasure Mountain maps, related to The Exile of Suzy Q.
    - Luny Piece, undated (Box 12, Folder 9)
      A few typescript pages, partially in French.
    - Miscellaneous Works, undated (Box 12, Folder 10)
      Includes "A Little Slavic Village in the Heart of Manhattan," a Veronica Saga family tree, and some unidentified typescript pages, possibly related to the unpublished Rosemary novel.
    - Questionable Papers, 1942-1978, undated (Box 12, Folder 11)
      This file contains various materials, including notes for Prophets Without Honor and other stories, various typescript pages, interview questions, and some miscellaneous correspondence.
    - Various Manuscript Fragments and Notes, undated (Box 12, Folder 12)
      Includes various unidentified typescript pages and notes. A few relate to Professor Mundy and Prophets Without Honor, and there are notes on Simon and Sylvie.
  - Subseries I.8: Other Notes and Notebooks, 1962-1964, undated
    This subseries contains notebooks and notes on various subjects.
    - Clippings on Young Socialites and Partying, 1964 April (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Notebook, 1963; Composition Notebook (Box 12, Folder 14)
      This notebook contains some notes related to Kathy, as well as serving as a personal notebooks with notes on her childbirth classes, shopping lists for the hospital, etc.
    - Notebook, undated; Pennant Winner Composition Book (Box 12, Folder 15)
      This notebook contains notes on Bourgeois Realism, Truman Capote vs. French intellectuals, and a draft of story "Pompeii in Red."
    - Notes on "Women Who Drink Too Much", circa 1962 (Box 12, Folder 16)
      Notes on articles by Neal Gilkyson Stuart from Ladies Home Journal and Readers Digest.
- Series II: Professional Files, 1956-1964, 1987, 2002-2011
  This series contains correspondence, contracts, clippings files, and items Moore received from her publisher René Julliard.
  There are also some professional topics covered in the correspondence, financial, tax, and legal files in Series III: Personal and Biographical Materials.
  - Subseries II.1: Correspondence, 1956-1964, 1987, 2002-2011
    This subseries includes correspondence with individuals, literary agents, and publishers, on a variety of professional issues. This correspondence was largerly maintained in one alphabetical set. The correspondence also includes condolence letters, mostly from professional contacts, written to Adam Kanarek after Moore's death in 1964, and a few folders of fan mail and correspondence from readers.
    The subseries also includes some later correspondence with Adam and Kevin Kanarek on subjects related to Moore.
    Correspondence and other materials related to Edouard de Laurot are filed in Series III: Personal and Biographical Materials.
    - Alfred A. Knopf, Inc., 1957-1964 (Box 12, Folder 17)
      Includes correspondence to Moore on reactions to the novel Young Assassins; correspondence on Prophets without Honor
    - Fernando Arrabal, 1960-1961, 2011 (Box 12, Folder 18)
      Includes a 2011 email to Kevin Kanarek with Arrabal's recollections of Moore.
    - Odette Arnaud, 1957-1964 (Box 12, Folder 19)
      French literary agent.
    - Arnoldo Mondadori Editore, 1957-1964, 1987, 2004 (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Atheneum Publishers, 1961 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Bantam Books, 1960-1963 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      Correspondence on the reissue and screenplay for Chocolates for Breakfast.
    - Peter Basch, 1958, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
      Photograph. Includes copy of Peter Basch Photographs: Beauties of the World, Fawcett, 1958. Includes negative for a partially nude image of Moore (unpublished); contact sheets for this photo shoot and other Basch photographs of Moore are filed in Series IV: Photographs..
    - Bernice Block, 1961-1962 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      Includes correspondence on the screenplay for Chocolates for Breakfast.
    - British Publishers and Agents, 1956-1963 (Box 13, Folder 5)
      Includes correspondence with Ursula Winant agent) and Longmans (publisher).
    - Leroy Breunig, 1950s, 2005 (Box 13, Folder 6)
      Breunig was a professor of French Literature at Barnard College. The 2005 correspondence is between Breunig's nephew and Kevin Kanarek.
    - Sidney Burrell, 1960 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      Burrell was a professor in the History Department at Barnard College.
    - Al Capp, 1963, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Condolences, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 9)
      This file contains several condolenece letters to Adam Kanarek following Moore's death in 1964. There are others in the individual correspondence files. The file also contains a bill for Moore's funeral and related expenses from Campbell Funeral Home.
    - Kurt Desch / German Publishers, 1956-1961 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - E. P. Dutton, 1961 (Box 13, Folder 11)
      Includes correspondence pertaining to Exile of Suzy-Q.
    - Fan Mail, 1956-1958 (Box 13, Folder 12)
      Correspondence relates to Chocolates for Breakfast.
    - Fawcett Publications, Inc., 1961-1964 (Box 13, Folder 13)
      Includes correspondence pertaining to East Side Story.
    - Robert Gottlieb (Simon and Schuster), 1963-1964, 2002 (Box 13, Folder 14)
      Includes some correspondence between Gottlieb and Adam Kanarek.
    - Juan Goyanarte, 1961-1962 (Box 13, Folder 15)
      Publisher in Argentina.
    - Grove Press, 1961 (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - Rust Hills (Esquire Magazine), 1961 (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - Franz Horch, 1957-1958 (Box 13, Folder 18)
      Literary agent
    - Israel, 1961 (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - J.B. Lippincott Company, 1962 (Box 13, Folder 20)
    - James Brown Associates, Inc., 1961 (Box 13, Folder 21)
      Correspondence pertains to the submission and rejection of Exile of Suzy-Q.
    - Japan, 1961-1962 (Box 13, Folder 22)
      Correspondence pertains to a payment dispute over Chocolates for Breakfast.
    - Jack Jolles, 1960-1961, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 23)
      Includes a condolence letter.
    - Julliard, 1957-1963 (Box 13, Folder 24)
    - Jacques Lanzmann, 1961 (Box 13, Folder 25)
    - Raymond Las Vergnas, 1961 (Box 13, Folder 26)
    - Last, 1964-1967; 2 folders (Box 19, Folder 11-12)
      This file contains financial material, particularly related to Mondadori, royalty reports, a few publisher letters, and material relating to Contemporary Authors appearance.
    - John Leggett (Harper & Brothers), 1961 (Box 13, Folder 27)
      Correspondence pertains to the rejection of Exile of Suzy-Q.
    - Carolyn Ruth Swift Lenz (Lyn Lenz), 1964, 2003, undated (Box 13, Folder 28)
      Lenz was Moore's teacher and friend at Rosemary Hall. The character of Ms. Rosen in Chocolates for Breakfast is based on Lenz. Correspondence includes her reaction to the novel, a letter of condolence, and a later letter to Adam Kanarek regarding his wish to put a stone marker on Moore's grave.
    - Little, Brown and Company, 1961 (Box 13, Folder 29)
      Correspondence regarding the submission and rejection of Exile of Suzy-Q. Includes comments from readers at the company.
    - Sterling Lord, 1957-1961 (Box 13, Folder 30)
      Literary agent. Includes agreement and correspondence.
    - Sylvie Marion, 1962 (Box 13, Folder 31)
    - Ann Martin--Correspondence to Robert Nedelkoff, 2008 (Box 13, Folder 32)
      Martin had written an early article about Pamela Moore; Nedelkoff contacted her about his own writings about Pamela Moore.
    - Jean Jacques Mayoux, 1960 (Box 13, Folder 33)
    - Monica McCall, 1956-1957 (Box 13, Folder 34)
      Literary agent. Includes correspondence pertaining to Chocolates for Breakfast, including reader's comments from Ladies Home Journal and Women's Home Companion.
    - New York Times Sunday Book Review, 1961 (Box 13, Folder 35)
      Contains typescript of a review of Gombrowicz's Ferryduke and a carbon of Moore's letter to the editor of the Sunday Book Review. Includes a clipping of the published letter to the editor.
    - Playboy, 1961 (Box 13, Folder 36)
      Rejection letter.
    - Reader Correspondence, 1956-1962 (Box 14, Folder 1)
      Reader correspondence; includes some drafts of replies from Moore.
    - Rinehart and Company, Inc., 1956 (Box 14, Folder 2)
      One item, an invitation to discuss the manuscript for Chocolates for Breakfast.
    - Simon and Schuster, 1962-1964 (Box 14, Folder 3)
      Includes letter from Moore on her time in Paris after the publication of Chocolates for Breakfast. Other correspondence pertains to The Horsy Set.
    - Milburn David Smith, Jr., 1964 September-December (Box 14, Folder 4)
      Copies of Jaguar magazine from December 1964 which includes an article on Moore. Also includes correspondence from Smith to Adam Kanarek with a litter from Don Fine (editor at Dell) to Smith with his recollections of Moore.
    - Constantin Tacou, 1958 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Jozef Wittlin, 1961-1964 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Subseries II.2: Contracts, 1956-1963
    This subseries contains contracts, signed and unsigned, for various editions and licensing rights to Moore's works. There is also a file of contract copies.
    Contracts for first editions remain filed with their corresponding manuscripts in Series I.
    - Contracts, 1957-1963 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Contracts (Copies), 1956-1961 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Subseries II.3: Clippings Files, 1950, 1956-1964, 1997-2014
    This subseries primarily consists of clippings related to the publication of Moore's novels: many were obtained from a clippings service. These are primarily in English and in French, although there are some items from the German and Italian presses, and others.
    There are also some later articles (2000-2014) related to Moore.
    - Clippings, 1950 (Box 14, Folder 9)
      Clipping on the junior riders at the National Horse Show; includes photograph of Moore.
    - Chocolates for Breakfast--Clippings, 1956-1957 (Box 14, Folder 10)
      In English.
    - Chocolates for Breakfast--Clippings, 1956-1957 (Box 14, Folder 11)
      Primarily in French. Includes some clippings in German, Italian, and other languages.
    - Chocolates for Breakfast--Clippings on Paperback Release; Screenplay, 1960 (Box 14, Folder 12)
      Includes short clipping on the book's release in paperback edition. Includes several clippings on the development of the screenplay for the novel.
    - Cosmopolitan, 1958, 1959 (Box 14, Folder 13)
      Two issues of the magazine; include mentions of Moore in articles about current writing.
    - East Side Story / The Pigeons of St. Marks--Goyanarte Catalog, 1961 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - East Side Story / The Pigeons of St. Marks--Clippings, 1960-1961 (Box 14, Folder 15)
      In English, French, Polish, and Italian. Includes a few typescript translations from French publications.
    - East Side Story / The Pigeons of St. Marks--Manuscripts/Typescripts of Related Items, 1961 (Box 14, Folder 16)
      These items were originally together in one plastic enclosure, filed in the clippings files. This folder includes typescripts of interview questions and answers, quotations, carbons of a few rejection letters from publishers, and a handwritten copy of an article published in Brazil.
    - The Exile of Suzy Q--Clippings, 1962 (Box 14, Folder 17)
      In French.
    - The Exile of Suzy Q--Clippings, 1962 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Paris Match Magazine, 1962 (Box 22, Folder 8)
      In French. Includes a short article on Moore.
    - The Horsy Set--Clippings, 1962-1964; 2 folders (Box 15, Folder 2-3)
      Primarily in English.
    - Obituaries, 1964 (Box 15, Folder 4)
      In English and in French.
    - Robert Nedelkoff, "The Remainder Table" The Baffler #10, 1997 (Box 15, Folder 5)
      Article on Moore.
    - "Great Girl Trash", 2000 (Box 15, Folder 6)
      Includes Chocolates for Breakfast.
    - Le Parisien Magazine, 2014 (Box 15, Folder 7)
      Magazine includes article on the reissue of Chocolates for Breakfast. In French.
  - Subseries II.4: Julliard--Promotional Materials and Souvenirs, 1956-1964
    This subseries contains items that Moore received from her publisher René Julliard.
    Moore received several items when Chocolates for Breakfast was published in France: a scarf, a set of dishes, and three matchbooks that were created as promotional items for the book.
    Two other items appear to have been issued as "souvenirs" after the death of René Julliard in 1962: a book, titled En Souvenir de René Julliard(1963), and a paperweight, which has an accompanying card on the stationary of Madame René Julliard (1964).
    - Chocolates for Breakfast--Matchbook, 1956 (Box 23)
      Matchbooks featuring the book's cover and a picture of Moore.
    - Set of Dishes, 1956 (Box Temporary Box C)
      French publisher René Julliard gave items to Moore to celebrate release of Chocolates for Breakfast in France, including this set of plates. The plates include signatures of authors and artists related to the publishing house. Moore's set has 11 8" plates. There should be 12 plates; #5 is missing from this set.
    - Scarf, 1956 (Box 23)
      Silkscreen scarf designed by Bernard Buffet, depicting book case of titles published by Julliard in 1956, including Chocolates for Breakfast.
    - En Souvenir de René Julliard. Paris: Julliard, 1963 (Box 20)
      Book. René Julliard, founder of Julliard, died in 1962.
    - Paperweight and Card, 1964 (Box 23)
      Lucite paperweight with green feather pen and René Julliard's signature. It includes handwritten card in French, indicating that the paperweight was created in memory of Julliard, who died in 1962.
- Series III: Personal and Biographical Materials, 1948-2013 [Bulk Dates: 1948-1964]
  This series contains personal and family correspondence, diaries, official documents, school files, sketchbooks, travel notes, and a set of financial, tax, and legal files.
  Photographs are filed in Series IV: Photographs.
  - Subseries III.1: Personal Correspondence and Related Materials, 1956-2013
    This subseries contains correspondence and related materials such as clippings, magazines, and personal documents.
    - Subseries III.1.1: Family, 1956-2002
      This subseries contains correspondence involving members of Moore's family. The correspondence is between Moore's family and Pamela Moore, Adam Kanarek, and Kevin Kanarek, with the exception of a few items sent to Isabel Moore by Jerry Asher.
      This series includes correspondence written during Moore's lifetime, as well as later correspondence between her family members.
      The subseries also contains a few other items – clippings, draft cards, postcards, and a life insurance policy – related to individual family members.
      - Adam Kanarek--Correspondence with Pamela Moore, 1957-1963 (Box 15, Folder 8)
      - Elaine Moore Moffat, 1957-1962, undated (Box 15, Folder 9)
        Correspondence with Isabel Moore, Pamela Moore, and Adam Kanarek. Also includes a photocopy of a typescript of what are apparently Elaine's notes/quotations from a memoir by Isabel Moore, going back to Isabel's childhood and ending with the end of her marriage to Don Moore.
      - Donald Moore--Correspondence to Kevin Kanarek, 1979-1986 (Box 15, Folder 10)
        Includes obituaries.
      - Donald Moore--Correspondence with Pamela Moore, and to Adam Kanarek, 1957-1966, 1979-1984, undated (Box 15, Folder 11)
      - Donald Moore--Draft Cards and Documents, 1942 (Box 15, Folder 12)
      - Isabel Moore--Correspondence from Jerry Asher, 1956 (Box 16, Folder 1)
        Asher was an MGM publicist and later a fan magazine writer.
      - Isabel Moore--Correspondence with Adam Kanarek, 1957-1964 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Isabel Moore--Correspondence with Pamela Moore, 1957-1958, undated (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - Isabel Moore--Forgive Me, My Darling--Advertisement and Memo, circa 1964 (Box 16, Folder 4)
        Isabel Moore wrote a memoir regarding Pamela Moore, but there are no known copies of the book. According to the "In the Next Room" essay in the Harper Perenniel edition of Chocolates for Breakfast, it was never published, although there were advance advertisements. There is a 9-page memo in the file with quotations and notes from the text in this file.
      - Isabel Moore--Press Clippings, 1939, 1962-1963 (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - Isabel Moore--Life Insurance Policy, 1936 (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - Postcards, Miscellaneous, 1950s-1960s (Box 16, Folder 7)
        Seven postcards. One was mailed to Adam Kanarek in 1953; the others are unsent.
    - Subseries III.1.2: Edouard de Laurot, and Others, 1956-1963, 1982, 2013
      This subseries contains correspondence from Moore to Laurot, as well as clippings, and several issues of Film Culture magazine.
      The correspondence file for Laurot is a photocopy of the original file kept by Jonas Mekas; Mekas retains the original file. This file contains correspondence from Moore to Laurot (given to Mekas for safe keeping by Laurot) and from Laurot to Mekas, some of which concern Moore.
      The subseries also contains clippings on Laurot and Mekas, and copies of Film Culture magazine, which they co-founded in the 1950s.
      This subseries also contains a few miscellaneous files kept by Pamela Moore. There is also a file of correspondence with journalists and friends in France. One of these dates to Moore's time in Paris. These files include business cards, clippings, correspondence, notes, drafts, etc.
      - Edouard de Laurot--Correspondence, 1956-1957, undated; Photocopies (Box 16, Folder 8)
        Photocopies in this file were provided by Jonas Mekas, who retains the originals. This file contains correspondence from Moore to Laurot (given to Mekas for safe keeping) and from Laurot to Mekas, some of which concern Moore.
      - Edouard de Laurot--Draft of Letter to Mr. Borde, undated (Box 16, Folder 9)
        Draft, with notes by Moore.
      - Edouard de Laurot and Jonas Mekas--Clippings, 1960 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Film Culture Magazine, 1955-1958; 2 folders (Box 16, Folder 11-12)
        Various issues.
      - Miscellaneous, 1956-1957, 1982, 2013 (Box 16, Folder 13)
        File contains notes, drafts, fragments, receipts, business cards, etc. dating to Moore's time in Paris. There are a few later items: a letter from school friend Barbara Montgomery to Alison Ehringer with her recollections about Moore and Adam Kanarek (1982) and a short postcard from George Morris to Kevin Kanarek (2013).
      - Pamela Moore--Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1957-1963 (Box 16, Folder 14)
        File contains a few pieces of correspondence, and sketches of furniture.
      - Pamela Moore--Miscellaneous Correspondence and Notes, 1958-1961, undated (Box 16, Folder 15)
        File contains correspondence, notes, articles, etc.
      - France--Journalists and Friends, 1957-1962 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Subseries III.2: Diaries, 1948-1964
    This subseries contains six diaries, kept between 1948 and 1964. Some diaries also contain clippings, notes, drafts of her writings, and other materials.
    There are also a few personal notes in a 1963 notebooks filed in Series I.8: Other Notes and Notebooks.
    - Diary, 1948 May-August; 1951 April-August; Red diary, with clasp (Box 24)
      Conditions Governing Access
      This diary is accessible, but please take care that the lock remains open during use.
    - Diary, 1952-1953, 1956; Gray "Ledger" (Box 25)
      Some portions of this were used as a creative journal, and the portion from 1956 was to record her emotions during the writing of Chocolates for Breakfast. Items inserted loosely inserted into the front of the diary have been removed and housed in an appropriate folder. See Box 17, Folder 12.
    - Diary--Inserted Items, 1952-1953, 1956; Gray "Ledger" (Box 17, Folder 12)
      Includes items inserted loosely inserted into the front of the diary: report card from Rosemary Hall, typescript of the story, "Veteran," with teacher's comments and grade, and clipping of Moore's first byline in the Greenwich Times. The diary itself is in Box 25.
    - Diary, 1953 May-1954 April; Small blue diary (Box 26)
    - Diary, 1956, 1959, 1961; Large red and black volume. (Box 27)
      Covers Moore's travels and her relationship with her family during 1956. Also includes telegrams from Moore's father, letters from Adam Kanarek, and other items. Includes draft and notes for "Heat."
    - Diary, 1959-1963; National Diary for 1961 (Box 28)
      Diary is used primarily for clippings, and also includes notes and outlines for Kathy.
    - Diary, 1963-1964; National Diary for 1961, with Officer of the Medical Examiner Sticker on Front (Box 29)
      This diary served both as a diary and a writing notebook. It includes drafts and notes for Kathy, Northscape, and several short stories and plays. There is a table of contents in the front of the volume. This volume also contains her last diary entries: entries and notes about her pregnancy and the birth of her son, and entries from 1964, including an entry for June 7th. This volume was used as evidence by the Office of the Medical Examiner, and the printed form sticker from the office is still affixed to the front of the volume.
      This diary is missing its spine and the binding is quite fragile. It is accessible at this time, but please handle with care.
  - Subseries III.3: Documents, 1956-1962
    This subseries contains Moore's drivers' license and passport.
    - Drivers' License, 1962 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Passport, 1956-1958 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Subseries III.4: Financial, Tax, and Legal Files, 1956-1967
    Moore maintained a set of financial, tax, and legal files that are primarily related to her failure to pay taxes in 1957. This led to ongoing issues with the Internal Revenue Service (IRS) in the United States. These files include correspondence, forms, subpoenas, warrants, notices of judgment, tax returns, bank statements, royalty reports, and other materials.
    A savings account book, a file on medical expenses, and a file of receipts also pertain to Moore's finances during this period.
    - Tax and Legal Files, 1957-1967; 3 folders (Box 19, Folder 3-5)
      File includes correspondence, forms, subpoenas, warrants, notices of judgment, tax returns, bank statements, receipts, and royalty reports. These are related to Moore's failure to pay income tax in 1957.
    - Savings Account Book, 1958 September-1959 August (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Medical, 1958 May-December (Box 19, Folder 7)
      Medical bills, and list of medical expenses for 1958.
    - Receipts--Columbia University, New York City, Paris, 1956-1957 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Subseries III.5: School Materials, 1949-1958
    This subseries contains school files from both Rosemary Hall and Barnard College.
    The Rosemary Hall files include school notebooks and a school magazine. There is an additional report card in Subseries III.2: Diaries (with the gray "ledger" diary). Moore's class photographs are filed in Series IV: Photographs.
    The Barnard College files include correspondence and other materials related to the submission of Moore's senior thesis and her progress towards the completion of her degree, as well as a copy of her senior thesis, other academic papers, notes, a yearbook, and Moore's diploma.
    - Rosemary Hall--School Notebooks, 1949-1950 (Box 17, Folder 1)
      With notes on French, Grammar, History, English, etc.
    - Rosemary Hall--Question Mark Magazine, 1949 October (Box 17, Folder 2)